<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Marathon | Coding and Running]]></title>
  <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/categories/marathon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-11-20T17:30:41-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Edwin Guzman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2016 NYC Marathon: Still Trying to Find Myself]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/11/17/2016-nyc-marathon-still-trying-to-find-myself/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-17T23:20:44-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/11/17/2016-nyc-marathon-still-trying-to-find-myself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been close to two weeks after the NYC marathon and I still don&rsquo;t know how to put everything that has happened into words. The feelings of pride, happiness, sadness, determination, and emptiness still lingers. The love outweighs the negativity but I can&rsquo;t help and feel slightly upset about how this training cycle concluded. Lots of factors went into the back-to-back Chicago and NYC marathon races and I can only learn from the experience.</p>

<h2>The Bad</h2>

<p>Quick statistics: In 2015 I ran the NYC Marathon in 2:59:24 and then two weeks later the NYRR 60K in 4:37:41. This year, I ran the Chicago Marathon in 2:58:05 (a PR) and then the NYC Marathon in 3:00:55.</p>

<p>I’m not sure how I did what I did last year, considering I feel fitter and stronger this year. A week before the NYC Marathon, however, I felt an intense pain in my right inner thigh, very close to the groin. I then took a few days off to rest well which halted my training, but I was suppose to rest and taper anyways. I was four miles into the NYC Marathon when I felt a slight pull and feelings of pain again. It was then that I knew that I had to slow down because it would be a tough marathon.</p>

<p>But, injury aside, I didn’t feel prepared for NYC. I don’t believe I lost any fitness from the Chicago Marathon which was about 4 weeks prior to NYC. Now that I had time to think about it, I was disappointed about how the Chicago Marathon unfolded and I was afraid of repeating the same situation in NYC. Luckily, because I went through it just recently, I felt better about failing this time around.</p>

<h2>The Good</h2>

<p>I had two Boston Qualifying races about one month apart, I ran with a bigger Queens Distance team, I saw many friends and family along the course, and I was able to share this marathon experience with my father who ran his first NYC Marathon. All of that made this NYC Marathon my favorite marathon yet. It was an incredible feeling to go through all of that in a span of a few hours, a fraction of which was the actual race.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:62.4537037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BMX9wmSjZxG/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Father and son ✌🏼️ Both Local Competitive 💪🏼 We trained hard, earned our spots, and now it&#39;s time: TCS NYC Marathon!🏃🏻🏃🏻 Not many can say that they will run a marathon with their father and for that I&#39;m truly grateful. #likefatherlikeson #queensdistance #tcsnycmarathon #marathoners #fam #😭</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-11-04T04:15:10+00:00">Nov 3, 2016 at 9:15pm PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<h1>TCS NYC Marathon</h1>

<p>My team set up another bus shuttle ride to Staten Island this year and it was a sleepy joy to meetup with teammates and other runners all going to run NYC, either again or for the first time. Being surrounded by first timers made the trip uneasy because I caught their nervousness but later regained control. After unloading, some of us headed to the Local Competitor area which now had so many Queens Distance runners. My father was with me this entire time and he was in awe about everything, especially since I kept telling him about everything that was around us. That truly made the experience amazing; how many can say they started off the NYC Marathon with their father?</p>

<p>The race started off well though it might’ve been faster that what I wanted to start off at. As I mentioned above, the slight pain at mile 4 made me settle into a steadier pace. Everything was going well and I was really enjoying the crowd. I pinned a small Mexican flag on my chest and I kept hearing “vamos Mexico!” which really filled me up with pride. (Note: I should really try adding my name next time.)</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BMff3NSD-SE/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Probably the most painful marathon I&#39;ve ever ran but still trying to smile. 🇲🇽 #queensdistance #tcsnycmarathon #stilllookinggood #vamosmexico</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-11-07T02:27:51+00:00">Nov 6, 2016 at 6:27pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<p>After the halfway point we were in Queens where I saw so many friends cheering either at the Mile 14 water station, in the streets, or at the mile 15 Queens Center for Progress cheering station. And then, it got lonely and painful. I started the slow and long trek up the Queensboro bridge and about a fourth of the way up, I was starting to get really tired, and this was with me slowing down. My heart rate just spiked up and I was working way too hard. It was around this point that Marie tapped me on my elbow as she sped on in front of me. It was great seeing her there and hoping she’d have a good marathon.</p>

<p>I soon after regain composure when I made it to 1st Ave. where one of my coworkers was waiting for me but I didn’t hear him! Going up 1st Ave. was tough, especially when I felt I was going at a steady 6:30 pace but was actually closer to 6:50 pace. That 20 second pace difference is very noticeable at this point as you’re tired but want to keep pushing. Fine, not a big deal, just need to keep running and make it at least past the Bronx; if I get back to Manhattan on 5th Ave. in one piece I’ll be happy.</p>

<p>I have a clear image of the first moment I stepped into the Bronx. During our training runs we run on the pedestrian side of the bridge and so we never get to run on the actual course. So as I stepped into the Bronx I now have this image of the first left corner and seeing a huge crowd waiting for us. The Bronx is mentally easily as I know all the turns very, very well… and so I just tune off and run. But, as I was approaching the Western Beef and the final turns in the Bronx, I kept hearing my name. I knew that Elizabeth and Anthony (fellow teammates) were going to wait for us in the Bronx at mile 21 but it was not mile 21 yet. So I look around and I clearly see my grandma and my cousin Nayeli. I’m a bit confused and I turn around again and I see my other cousins, aunts, and uncles and I’m so surprised. This is the part that I can’t describe; I was surprised, in euphoria, and too emotional. I began to choke a bit as I felt a sob coming on but just had to put that aside and try to finish well&ndash;I didn’t want them cheering for me on a run which could have ended worse than it did.</p>

<p>With that, I did make it to Manhattan in one piece. It was running down 5th Ave. that further broke me down as I took a few walking breaks due to a mixture of fatigue and pain in my leg (not necessarily cramping since that came later around mile 24). Eventually, I made my way to the end right after waving at my family who were cheering for me on 59th St.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:37.4537037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BMe-3HajHlP/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">And we&#39;re done! It was a very tough marathon, especially coming off Chicago in early October, but my heart was all in it. So even though I didn&#39;t reach my goal, I still Boston Qualified and had the most fun I ever had in a marathon. I tried to focus more on everyone who was out there cheering and calling my name. It was even better knowing how many friends were tracking me #nopressure. And when I got to mile 20 in the Bronx I saw my family there! My abuelita, my aunts and uncles, and cousins. It was so unexpected that I choked up and got teary 😭. And seeing my mom, aunt, and siblings near the end again was awesome. So a huge thank you to everyone! ❤️ And a great sign by my sister @karennhaze. #likefatherlikeson #queensdistance #tcsnycmarathon #fam #love #marathoners #seeyousoonboston</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-11-06T21:39:29+00:00">Nov 6, 2016 at 1:39pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<h2>Closing the Year</h2>

<p>Pain. I finished the marathon cycle in a lot of pain. I have never felt that much pain in my legs after completing a marathon and I hope not to feel that again. I was trying to wait for my father but only managed to bump into Jose, Catherine, and Lori. The walk to get the poncho and exit Central Park was awful. I couldn’t move too fast and if I did it just made the pain worse.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/blog-images/2016-nyc-marathon.jpg" width="450" height="600" title="&lsquo;Reunited with my father after the NYC Marathon.&rsquo; &lsquo;Reunited with my father after the NYC Marathon.&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve gotten up to this point and are wondering about the title, so am I. I had two great marathons which other runners would love to achieve, but I am personally not satisfied with the execution. As I mentioned before, they were great times but I faded after about 20 miles into both races. What I&rsquo;m truly getting at is that I&rsquo;m still trying to find myself as a runner. It sounds banal but I&rsquo;m just learning how competitive and how much more I want to achieve that I don&rsquo;t know where I&rsquo;ll stop, if at all.</p>

<p>Everyone learns something about themselves after running a marathon; you never really are the same after crossing the finish line. It wasn&rsquo;t so much this race but the whole experience that really changed me.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chicago Marathon Love]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/10/28/chicago-marathon-love/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-28T22:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/10/28/chicago-marathon-love</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m overwhelmed and my heart is beginning to race as the plane prepares to take off. I then grin as I see my siblings' excited and nervous faces as we lift off; and with that we are off to Chicago! I went to Chicago for the marathon and came back with a new marathon personal best. Best of all, my teammates and siblings were there to enjoy the city of Chicago and our journey to another 26.2 mile race.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:62.4537037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BLPy9BHjh8x/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Great first day in Chicago! It was my sibling&#39;s first time on a plane and seeing their faces during take off was wonderful. Glad to be with them and my teammates in a new city, sight seeing and getting ready for Sunday. #family #chicago #chicagomarathon</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-10-07T03:35:26+00:00">Oct 6, 2016 at 8:35pm PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>When people ask me about the Chicago Marathon and the trip, I don&rsquo;t know how to articulate everything I went through&ndash;there was a lot going on and it all went by fast. The trip and marathong were amazing experiences and I try not to look at the negatives too critically, but there were bumps along the way. So let&rsquo;s start from the beginning.</p>

<h2>Family Trip</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s hard to plan family trips but I really wanted my siblings to go with me to Chicago, not just for their support, but because it would be their first time flying to a different city. Perhaps we walked around being tourist for too long and that wasn&rsquo;t a smart move, but it was fun checking out the Willis Tower, the Chicago Marathon Expo, the local pizza and hotdog venues, the Jordan store, the bridges, Wrigley Field, and the bean at Gateway Park. They are older now and they can (more or less) take care of themselves, but I still worried when they went out alone!</p>

<h2>Chicago International 5K</h2>

<p>Maria and Bryan ran the Chicago International 5K and that was an exciting prelude to the marathon. It was a chilly morning and Bryan was a bit nervous about this race. He wasn&rsquo;t sure how fast he would run, considering he barely trained for the race, but had a good race plan in mind. He didn&rsquo;t go out too fast and even though he was smiling at mile 2, he was suffering.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog-images/chicago-5k.jpg" title="&lsquo;Maria and Bryan at the Chicago International 5K.&rsquo; &lsquo;Maria and Bryan at the Chicago International 5K.&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>But, as you can tell, Bryan had a fun time; something we sometimes forget to do on race day.</p>

<h2>Marathon Day</h2>

<p>We had a large team dinner the night before the race which was fantastic. There were eight runners from our team, one who is not part of our team (yet), and many family members eating pasta and bread. It was a good time and that helped ease the nerves.</p>

<p>The morning of the race, my siblings and I rode to the starting area. There were a couple of last minute details I was bothered with:</p>

<ul>
<li>I realized I didn&rsquo;t have my heart rate monitor with me.</li>
<li>It was cold but not cold enough for arm warmers so I took them off.</li>
<li>I was confused about the starting area for my wave and corral. This meant that I waiting a bit longer on line for a porta-potty and so had to rush to get into my corral. I had a few minutes to spare from the corral closing.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:45.787037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BLWl9GkDI8h/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Before the start of the Chicago Marathon. Being dropped off by my siblings was great and really helped me pushed when I needed it the most towards the end of the race. #queensdistance #chicagomarathon #siblings #26point2</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-10-09T18:56:32+00:00">Oct 9, 2016 at 11:56am PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<p>The best part of the morning was the awkward and loving goodbye from my siblings.</p>

<h2>Marathon Race</h2>

<p>I was ready for this race. I wasn&rsquo;t mentally ready for a 2:47:00 to 2:50:00 marathon time though. Whoa, 2:47?! According to my NYRR Bronx 10 Mile time of 58:47, some race predictors said I could run around 2:47:00&hellip; but like I said, I wasn&rsquo;t too mentally ready for that. Perhaps that&rsquo;s not the best way to put it. I was confident in my training but jumping from 2:59 to 2:47 is a big deal and not having run that fast for that long before, I was wary. Thankfully, Luciano helped ease that thought away by explaining how he himself did it. It was possible, but could I do it?</p>

<p>I wanted it and I was going to go for it. If there&rsquo;s anything I learned from this marathon it&rsquo;s to really let go of your fear and just go for it. It sounds cliche but if you fail, you can try again, and if you succeed, then more power to you.</p>

<p>With that in mind, I start off running at a very comfortable pace, knowing very well that it was only because it was just the beginning. We ran the first few miles of the course a few days prior so we knew that the GPS signal would be off and I therefore had to mentally track my pace. Turns out that I paced it well for the first 5K but then went too fast for the second 5K. After that, everything was very steady.</p>

<p>Splits - pace:</p>

<ul>
<li>5K - 6:21</li>
<li>10K - 6:15</li>
<li>15K - 6:20</li>
<li>Half - 6:21 - Time: 1:22:45</li>
<li>25K - 6:31</li>
<li>30 - 6:20 - Time: 1:58:34</li>
</ul>


<p><br />
<img class="left" src="/images/blog-images/chicago-mid.jpg" width="400" height="550" title="&lsquo;Mid race.&rsquo; &lsquo;Mid race.&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The first 30 kilometers was perfect. Then, as I approached mile 20 in around 2:07:00, I began to feel a tightness in my right calf. I can&rsquo;t sure exactly what the reason was but I don&rsquo;t think I drank enough water or took in enough gels&ndash;in fact I took in only one gel around mile 20. I was afraid of getting a stomach cramp and instead ended up getting a bad leg cramp. It was dissapointing approaching mile 23 and having to take short walking breaks to ease up the legs and then continue. Worst of all, I approached mile 26 and my right hamstring completely pulled. I couldn&rsquo;t walk without pain and just had to completely stop. I massaged really well and just thought about finishing&ndash;I WAS SO CLOSE! And as I was walking to ease up the cramp I kept hearing my name.</p>

<p>When you&rsquo;re that far into a marathon, it&rsquo;s hard to really think straight. It&rsquo;s not like the halfway point where you can see your family standing by cheering for you. I couldn&rsquo;t manage to look around to see who was cheering me on and that&rsquo;s fine; I just looked ahead to the finish line and kept running.</p>

<p>Splits - pace:</p>

<ul>
<li>35K - 6:55</li>
<li>40K - 8:29</li>
<li>Finish: 2:58:05</li>
</ul>


<p><br />
<img class="left" src="/images/blog-images/chicago-final.jpg" width="450" height="600" title="&lsquo;Post race with a new marathon medal.&rsquo; &lsquo;Post race with a new marathon medal.&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I may have failed to reach my initial goal of 2:55 but I still went through it all with a new personal best. When people mention the PR they are excited, but I can&rsquo;t get too excited about it. I&rsquo;m not succumbing to the negativity of a bad race, but it&rsquo;s more about thinking of this race as a step towards a better race. I&rsquo;m happy with the PR but know I can do so much better and right now that&rsquo;s the drive I need. The Chicago Marathon went perfectly well for 20 miles or so and it&rsquo;s that effort that will help towards racing the NYC Marathon (but that&rsquo;s a different story!).</p>

<p>Would I run Chicago again? Yes. Will I run it next year? Perhaps. I&rsquo;m not too sure what 2017 will bring but I do know that for the Boston Marathon I will have my siblings, teammates, and now my parents&ndash;MY DAD BOSTON QUALIFIED!&ndash;supporting me. Love paves the way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
