<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Coding and Running]]></title>
  <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-11-21T23:03:58-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Edwin Guzman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2017 Fall Marathons Recap]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2017/11/20/fall-marathons-recap/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-20T22:28:08-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2017/11/20/fall-marathons-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Chicago</h2>

<p>I was 17 miles into the Chicago Marathon when I panicked. I was cruising miles 11 through 15 at low 6:20s pace per mile, just barely reaching into the marathon goal pace of 6:17 pace per mile. Suddenly, I felt an intense pain in my left abdomen. I&rsquo;ve felt this pain before when I tried to race, mostly untrained and recovering from an injury, at the 2016 Brooklyn Half. I was forced to stop and walk the pain away. Naturally, I didn&rsquo;t want that to happen again during this marathon, so I panicked.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/chicago-expo.jpg' width='450' height='550' title='At the Chicago Marathon expo.'><span class='caption-text'>At the Chicago Marathon expo.</span></span></p>

<p>I tried to battle one bad thought after another; but once the pain felt unbearable, I just had to stop and walk it off. The pain went away soon after. I gradually returned to a nice rhythm, hitting a 6:44 19th mile. Unfortunately, I didn&rsquo;t mentally recover from that setback and, along with my body giving up and not willing to keep running fast, I gave up. The first, second, and third goal for the race slipped away and so did my resolve to finish—I just wanted to walk away and try again at a later date. But I couldn’t quit with all the training and everything else I went through in the past few months.</p>

<p>Days like these when everything goes awry at a goal race happens. Still, you should make the best out of the situation. It was hard to. I&rsquo;m not sure what I would&rsquo;ve done if it wasn&rsquo;t for those helping me right after the marathon. Words of encouragement go a long way, but I couldn&rsquo;t help not being upset. Being upset is acceptable. But, not seeing my teammates after they finished their own races was unacceptable. I took the next hour or so to try to rationalize the unexpected disappointment before making my way to the post-marathon meet-up spot.</p>

<p>The following day I tried to figure out what went wrong. I wasn&rsquo;t upset about not meeting my goals; I was (irrationally) upset about letting others down. I was upset about all the time and effort I put in every day with nothing to show. I was upset about giving up.</p>

<p>Looking back now, all those positive and negative feelings were useful. They gave me a deeper appreciation for what I&rsquo;m trying to accomplish. Until the day comes when I️ do meet my goals, it&rsquo;s just a matter of working hard and looking toward the future.</p>

<h2>Training</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/20-miler-lr.png' width='425' height='525' title='Long Run - 20 miler in Central Park'><span class='caption-text'>Long Run - 20 miler in Central Park</span></span></p>

<p>This past marathon training cycle was the hardest one yet. Instead of doing a seven day training cycle with one or two rest days, I had an 11- or 12-day training cycle with one rest day in between. I practically ran everyday for over a week, and that was new to me. I also incorporated a lot of upper and lower body strength training. The most enjoyable form of cross training was climbing high walls and solving problems bouldering. Some of my favorite running workouts were the 20 milers where I averaged around 6:35 pace per mile, something I didn’t get close to doing last year. I even set a personal best at the NYRR 18 mile tune-up averaging a 6:23 pace, which helped boost my confidence for the Chicago Marathon.</p>

<p>When I look back at the past few months, I realized that getting through all that work was not difficult. Waking up before 5 AM to start my long runs wasn’t hard. Working out twice a day wasn’t hard. Eating better to maintain shape, recover, and fuel for the next run wasn’t hard. What was hard, however, was going through agony and emotional distress that came from the <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/09/04/politics/daca-dreamers-immigration-program/index.html">dismantling of DACA</a>.</p>

<p>DACA was rescinded and I was devastated. Approximately 800,000 people in the U.S. with DACA are now in a state of limbo regarding their residency in a country they call home. Those with DACA just have to keep living day to day like everyone else, knowing that at a moment&rsquo;s notice they can be deported to their &lsquo;home&rsquo; country. At work we launched a <a href="https://www.nypl.org/discovery">project</a> I had been working on for over a year, but I couldn’t be happy about the launch because it happened the same day. It was a dark time, and I wanted to be alone to make sense of the situation.</p>

<p>That’s not to say I didn’t have support. Coworkers, friends, and family members reached out and helped spread positive messages—a coworker&rsquo;s simple tweet was so moving that it left me speechless and teary in the office. Everything was greatly appreciated.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/dismantlingdaca.png' width='350' height='400' title='<a href="http://latinousa.org/episode/dismantling-daca/">Dismantling DACA Podcast</a><br>Image Courtesy of NPR Latino USA'><span class='caption-text'><a href="http://latinousa.org/episode/dismantling-daca/">Dismantling DACA Podcast</a><br>Image Courtesy of NPR Latino USA</span></span></p>

<p>What worried me the most was what the younger generation is going through. Most are still in school and don’t have a plan after graduation. That realization didn’t hit me until an <a href="http://latinousa.org/episode/dismantling-daca/">NPR podcast</a> made me tear up during a run. Listening about what others are going through and remembering what it was like hurt. I am glad, however, that we have communities to help those who need it.</p>

<p>I’m at a point where I’m doing what I love, and that’s not something I can take for granted. I never felt more like myself waking up before 5 AM and arriving at Flushing Meadow Park by 5:30 to start a 20 miler, or going through a tough speed session in the morning and then a strength session in the afternoon. Mentally going through training like a &ldquo;professional&rdquo;, looking forward to every run, and maintaining a consistent schedule made me feel unstoppable. I made everything a habit and cared enough that those day to day habits were not difficult to accomplish. Even though this was the first time I trained like this, it felt natural.</p>

<h2>NYC</h2>

<p>I have so much to say about the NYC Marathon that I cannot write it all down. I️ had to first recover from the Chicago Marathon. Two weeks after the race, I️ tested out the legs by doing two medium long runs. I️ felt confident enough to be able to give another decent shot at the marathon. At a certain point during the NYC marathon, however, I started to feel my legs seizing up, so I took it easy aiming just to finish and have fun.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BbBBz7chuWI/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Here we go again! The Guzman trio are ready for this weekend’s races. Bryan is racing the Dash to the Finish 5K, and my dad and I are racing the NYC Marathon. • It’s time to get over the disappointment at Chicago and give the marathon another shot. It’s hard not to be positive with my teammates’ and coworkers’ support. #queensdistance #nycmarathon #abbotdash5k #teamwork</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A post shared by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2017-11-03T02:18:57+00:00">Nov 2, 2017 at 7:18pm PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<p> <script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script></p>

<p>It’s difficult to not enjoy and have fun racing a marathon where you live. My coworker Greg made a poster of the marathon course highlighting what time I’d be at specific locations. I was able to catch him in the Bronx cheering, as well as other coworkers in Brooklyn and Manhattan. My cousins, aunts, uncles, and grandmother who live in the Bronx were set up in the same location where they, to my surprise, were located last year. Teammates volunteered at Mile 14 and 15 in Queens and passing them gave me motivation before tackling the Queensboro Bridge. And my family was also located right before the Queensboro Bridge and at later at Mile 25.5. It’s the fourth year consecutive year they come out for me. All the love, best wishes, and support is what makes the NYC Marathon my favorite marathon.</p>

<h2>Team</h2>

<p>I may not have accomplished the specific time that I wanted to run at the Chicago Marathon, but I accomplished so much more. It’s the drive and encouragement that I️, along with Kevin and Maria, try to give everyone in our team that makes them strive for more. So when I hear about PRs, surpassed expectations, or just completing a marathon which they’ve always dreamed of doing, I know I’m heading in the right direction helping them out.</p>

<p>This is the first (and maybe last) blog post of this year, but suffice it to say that this whole year culminated at a high point at the NYC Marathon. My outlook on DACA being rescinded and the failure at the Chicago Marathon is the same as all aspects in my life right now — optimistic and striving for more.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BbQYo1chqV4/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">We started 2017 by running and finishing the Boston Marathon side-by-side, and now we finished the year by both running the NYC Marathon. Never take anything for granted. • #bostonmarathon #tcsnycmarathon #likefatherlikeson</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A post shared by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2017-11-09T01:27:02+00:00">Nov 8, 2017 at 5:27pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>


<p> <script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script></p>

<p>* A big thanks to everyone who supported me in the past few months and to those who helped look over this post!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2016 NYC Marathon: Still Trying to Find Myself]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/11/17/2016-nyc-marathon-still-trying-to-find-myself/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-17T23:20:44-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/11/17/2016-nyc-marathon-still-trying-to-find-myself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been close to two weeks after the NYC marathon and I still don&rsquo;t know how to put everything that has happened into words. The feelings of pride, happiness, sadness, determination, and emptiness still lingers. The love outweighs the negativity but I can&rsquo;t help and feel slightly upset about how this training cycle concluded. Lots of factors went into the back-to-back Chicago and NYC marathon races and I can only learn from the experience.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Bad</h2>

<p>Quick statistics: In 2015 I ran the NYC Marathon in 2:59:24 and then two weeks later the NYRR 60K in 4:37:41. This year, I ran the Chicago Marathon in 2:58:05 (a PR) and then the NYC Marathon in 3:00:55.</p>

<p>I’m not sure how I did what I did last year, considering I feel fitter and stronger this year. A week before the NYC Marathon, however, I felt an intense pain in my right inner thigh, very close to the groin. I then took a few days off to rest well which halted my training, but I was suppose to rest and taper anyways. I was four miles into the NYC Marathon when I felt a slight pull and feelings of pain again. It was then that I knew that I had to slow down because it would be a tough marathon.</p>

<p>But, injury aside, I didn’t feel prepared for NYC. I don’t believe I lost any fitness from the Chicago Marathon which was about 4 weeks prior to NYC. Now that I had time to think about it, I was disappointed about how the Chicago Marathon unfolded and I was afraid of repeating the same situation in NYC. Luckily, because I went through it just recently, I felt better about failing this time around.</p>

<h2>The Good</h2>

<p>I had two Boston Qualifying races about one month apart, I ran with a bigger Queens Distance team, I saw many friends and family along the course, and I was able to share this marathon experience with my father who ran his first NYC Marathon. All of that made this NYC Marathon my favorite marathon yet. It was an incredible feeling to go through all of that in a span of a few hours, a fraction of which was the actual race.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:62.4537037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BMX9wmSjZxG/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Father and son ✌🏼️ Both Local Competitive 💪🏼 We trained hard, earned our spots, and now it&#39;s time: TCS NYC Marathon!🏃🏻🏃🏻 Not many can say that they will run a marathon with their father and for that I&#39;m truly grateful. #likefatherlikeson #queensdistance #tcsnycmarathon #marathoners #fam #😭</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-11-04T04:15:10+00:00">Nov 3, 2016 at 9:15pm PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<h1>TCS NYC Marathon</h1>

<p>My team set up another bus shuttle ride to Staten Island this year and it was a sleepy joy to meetup with teammates and other runners all going to run NYC, either again or for the first time. Being surrounded by first timers made the trip uneasy because I caught their nervousness but later regained control. After unloading, some of us headed to the Local Competitor area which now had so many Queens Distance runners. My father was with me this entire time and he was in awe about everything, especially since I kept telling him about everything that was around us. That truly made the experience amazing; how many can say they started off the NYC Marathon with their father?</p>

<p>The race started off well though it might’ve been faster that what I wanted to start off at. As I mentioned above, the slight pain at mile 4 made me settle into a steadier pace. Everything was going well and I was really enjoying the crowd. I pinned a small Mexican flag on my chest and I kept hearing “vamos Mexico!” which really filled me up with pride. (Note: I should really try adding my name next time.)</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BMff3NSD-SE/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Probably the most painful marathon I&#39;ve ever ran but still trying to smile. 🇲🇽 #queensdistance #tcsnycmarathon #stilllookinggood #vamosmexico</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-11-07T02:27:51+00:00">Nov 6, 2016 at 6:27pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<p>After the halfway point we were in Queens where I saw so many friends cheering either at the Mile 14 water station, in the streets, or at the mile 15 Queens Center for Progress cheering station. And then, it got lonely and painful. I started the slow and long trek up the Queensboro bridge and about a fourth of the way up, I was starting to get really tired, and this was with me slowing down. My heart rate just spiked up and I was working way too hard. It was around this point that Marie tapped me on my elbow as she sped on in front of me. It was great seeing her there and hoping she’d have a good marathon.</p>

<p>I soon after regain composure when I made it to 1st Ave. where one of my coworkers was waiting for me but I didn’t hear him! Going up 1st Ave. was tough, especially when I felt I was going at a steady 6:30 pace but was actually closer to 6:50 pace. That 20 second pace difference is very noticeable at this point as you’re tired but want to keep pushing. Fine, not a big deal, just need to keep running and make it at least past the Bronx; if I get back to Manhattan on 5th Ave. in one piece I’ll be happy.</p>

<p>I have a clear image of the first moment I stepped into the Bronx. During our training runs we run on the pedestrian side of the bridge and so we never get to run on the actual course. So as I stepped into the Bronx I now have this image of the first left corner and seeing a huge crowd waiting for us. The Bronx is mentally easily as I know all the turns very, very well… and so I just tune off and run. But, as I was approaching the Western Beef and the final turns in the Bronx, I kept hearing my name. I knew that Elizabeth and Anthony (fellow teammates) were going to wait for us in the Bronx at mile 21 but it was not mile 21 yet. So I look around and I clearly see my grandma and my cousin Nayeli. I’m a bit confused and I turn around again and I see my other cousins, aunts, and uncles and I’m so surprised. This is the part that I can’t describe; I was surprised, in euphoria, and too emotional. I began to choke a bit as I felt a sob coming on but just had to put that aside and try to finish well&ndash;I didn’t want them cheering for me on a run which could have ended worse than it did.</p>

<p>With that, I did make it to Manhattan in one piece. It was running down 5th Ave. that further broke me down as I took a few walking breaks due to a mixture of fatigue and pain in my leg (not necessarily cramping since that came later around mile 24). Eventually, I made my way to the end right after waving at my family who were cheering for me on 59th St.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:37.4537037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BMe-3HajHlP/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">And we&#39;re done! It was a very tough marathon, especially coming off Chicago in early October, but my heart was all in it. So even though I didn&#39;t reach my goal, I still Boston Qualified and had the most fun I ever had in a marathon. I tried to focus more on everyone who was out there cheering and calling my name. It was even better knowing how many friends were tracking me #nopressure. And when I got to mile 20 in the Bronx I saw my family there! My abuelita, my aunts and uncles, and cousins. It was so unexpected that I choked up and got teary 😭. And seeing my mom, aunt, and siblings near the end again was awesome. So a huge thank you to everyone! ❤️ And a great sign by my sister @karennhaze. #likefatherlikeson #queensdistance #tcsnycmarathon #fam #love #marathoners #seeyousoonboston</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-11-06T21:39:29+00:00">Nov 6, 2016 at 1:39pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<h2>Closing the Year</h2>

<p>Pain. I finished the marathon cycle in a lot of pain. I have never felt that much pain in my legs after completing a marathon and I hope not to feel that again. I was trying to wait for my father but only managed to bump into Jose, Catherine, and Lori. The walk to get the poncho and exit Central Park was awful. I couldn’t move too fast and if I did it just made the pain worse.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/2016-nyc-marathon.jpg" width="450" height="600" title="Reunited with my father after the NYC Marathon." alt="Reunited with my father after the NYC Marathon."></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve gotten up to this point and are wondering about the title, so am I. I had two great marathons which other runners would love to achieve, but I am personally not satisfied with the execution. As I mentioned before, they were great times but I faded after about 20 miles into both races. What I&rsquo;m truly getting at is that I&rsquo;m still trying to find myself as a runner. It sounds banal but I&rsquo;m just learning how competitive and how much more I want to achieve that I don&rsquo;t know where I&rsquo;ll stop, if at all.</p>

<p>Everyone learns something about themselves after running a marathon; you never really are the same after crossing the finish line. It wasn&rsquo;t so much this race but the whole experience that really changed me.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chicago Marathon Love]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/10/28/chicago-marathon-love/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-28T22:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/10/28/chicago-marathon-love</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m overwhelmed and my heart is beginning to race as the plane prepares to take off. I then grin as I see my siblings' excited and nervous faces as we lift off; and with that we are off to Chicago! I went to Chicago for the marathon and came back with a new marathon personal best. Best of all, my teammates and siblings were there to enjoy the city of Chicago and our journey to another 26.2 mile race.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:62.4537037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BLPy9BHjh8x/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Great first day in Chicago! It was my sibling&#39;s first time on a plane and seeing their faces during take off was wonderful. Glad to be with them and my teammates in a new city, sight seeing and getting ready for Sunday. #family #chicago #chicagomarathon</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-10-07T03:35:26+00:00">Oct 6, 2016 at 8:35pm PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>When people ask me about the Chicago Marathon and the trip, I don&rsquo;t know how to articulate everything I went through&ndash;there was a lot going on and it all went by fast. The trip and marathong were amazing experiences and I try not to look at the negatives too critically, but there were bumps along the way. So let&rsquo;s start from the beginning.</p>

<h2>Family Trip</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s hard to plan family trips but I really wanted my siblings to go with me to Chicago, not just for their support, but because it would be their first time flying to a different city. Perhaps we walked around being tourist for too long and that wasn&rsquo;t a smart move, but it was fun checking out the Willis Tower, the Chicago Marathon Expo, the local pizza and hotdog venues, the Jordan store, the bridges, Wrigley Field, and the bean at Gateway Park. They are older now and they can (more or less) take care of themselves, but I still worried when they went out alone!</p>

<h2>Chicago International 5K</h2>

<p>Maria and Bryan ran the Chicago International 5K and that was an exciting prelude to the marathon. It was a chilly morning and Bryan was a bit nervous about this race. He wasn&rsquo;t sure how fast he would run, considering he barely trained for the race, but had a good race plan in mind. He didn&rsquo;t go out too fast and even though he was smiling at mile 2, he was suffering.</p>

<p><img src="http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/chicago-5k.jpg" title="Maria and Bryan at the Chicago International 5K." alt="Maria and Bryan at the Chicago International 5K."></p>

<p>But, as you can tell, Bryan had a fun time; something we sometimes forget to do on race day.</p>

<h2>Marathon Day</h2>

<p>We had a large team dinner the night before the race which was fantastic. There were eight runners from our team, one who is not part of our team (yet), and many family members eating pasta and bread. It was a good time and that helped ease the nerves.</p>

<p>The morning of the race, my siblings and I rode to the starting area. There were a couple of last minute details I was bothered with:</p>

<ul>
<li>I realized I didn&rsquo;t have my heart rate monitor with me.</li>
<li>It was cold but not cold enough for arm warmers so I took them off.</li>
<li>I was confused about the starting area for my wave and corral. This meant that I waiting a bit longer on line for a porta-potty and so had to rush to get into my corral. I had a few minutes to spare from the corral closing.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:45.787037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BLWl9GkDI8h/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Before the start of the Chicago Marathon. Being dropped off by my siblings was great and really helped me pushed when I needed it the most towards the end of the race. #queensdistance #chicagomarathon #siblings #26point2</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-10-09T18:56:32+00:00">Oct 9, 2016 at 11:56am PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<p>The best part of the morning was the awkward and loving goodbye from my siblings.</p>

<h2>Marathon Race</h2>

<p>I was ready for this race. I wasn&rsquo;t mentally ready for a 2:47:00 to 2:50:00 marathon time though. Whoa, 2:47?! According to my NYRR Bronx 10 Mile time of 58:47, some race predictors said I could run around 2:47:00&hellip; but like I said, I wasn&rsquo;t too mentally ready for that. Perhaps that&rsquo;s not the best way to put it. I was confident in my training but jumping from 2:59 to 2:47 is a big deal and not having run that fast for that long before, I was wary. Thankfully, Luciano helped ease that thought away by explaining how he himself did it. It was possible, but could I do it?</p>

<p>I wanted it and I was going to go for it. If there&rsquo;s anything I learned from this marathon it&rsquo;s to really let go of your fear and just go for it. It sounds cliche but if you fail, you can try again, and if you succeed, then more power to you.</p>

<p>With that in mind, I start off running at a very comfortable pace, knowing very well that it was only because it was just the beginning. We ran the first few miles of the course a few days prior so we knew that the GPS signal would be off and I therefore had to mentally track my pace. Turns out that I paced it well for the first 5K but then went too fast for the second 5K. After that, everything was very steady.</p>

<p>Splits - pace:</p>

<ul>
<li>5K - 6:21</li>
<li>10K - 6:15</li>
<li>15K - 6:20</li>
<li>Half - 6:21 - Time: 1:22:45</li>
<li>25K - 6:31</li>
<li>30 - 6:20 - Time: 1:58:34</li>
</ul>


<p><br />
<img class="left" src="http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/chicago-mid.jpg" width="400" height="550" title="Mid race." alt="Mid race."></p>

<p>The first 30 kilometers was perfect. Then, as I approached mile 20 in around 2:07:00, I began to feel a tightness in my right calf. I can&rsquo;t sure exactly what the reason was but I don&rsquo;t think I drank enough water or took in enough gels&ndash;in fact I took in only one gel around mile 20. I was afraid of getting a stomach cramp and instead ended up getting a bad leg cramp. It was dissapointing approaching mile 23 and having to take short walking breaks to ease up the legs and then continue. Worst of all, I approached mile 26 and my right hamstring completely pulled. I couldn&rsquo;t walk without pain and just had to completely stop. I massaged really well and just thought about finishing&ndash;I WAS SO CLOSE! And as I was walking to ease up the cramp I kept hearing my name.</p>

<p>When you&rsquo;re that far into a marathon, it&rsquo;s hard to really think straight. It&rsquo;s not like the halfway point where you can see your family standing by cheering for you. I couldn&rsquo;t manage to look around to see who was cheering me on and that&rsquo;s fine; I just looked ahead to the finish line and kept running.</p>

<p>Splits - pace:</p>

<ul>
<li>35K - 6:55</li>
<li>40K - 8:29</li>
<li>Finish: 2:58:05</li>
</ul>


<p><br />
<img class="left" src="http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/chicago-final.jpg" width="450" height="600" title="Post race with a new marathon medal." alt="Post race with a new marathon medal."></p>

<p>I may have failed to reach my initial goal of 2:55 but I still went through it all with a new personal best. When people mention the PR they are excited, but I can&rsquo;t get too excited about it. I&rsquo;m not succumbing to the negativity of a bad race, but it&rsquo;s more about thinking of this race as a step towards a better race. I&rsquo;m happy with the PR but know I can do so much better and right now that&rsquo;s the drive I need. The Chicago Marathon went perfectly well for 20 miles or so and it&rsquo;s that effort that will help towards racing the NYC Marathon (but that&rsquo;s a different story!).</p>

<p>Would I run Chicago again? Yes. Will I run it next year? Perhaps. I&rsquo;m not too sure what 2017 will bring but I do know that for the Boston Marathon I will have my siblings, teammates, and now my parents&ndash;MY DAD BOSTON QUALIFIED!&ndash;supporting me. Love paves the way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Four: Fifty Six]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/09/08/four-fifty-six/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-08T21:45:58-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/09/08/four-fifty-six</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The past few months have been crazy and I&rsquo;m still trying to process and understand it all. I will write another blog post to try and summarize the past few months, but for now I&rsquo;ll discuss the four minutes and fifty six seconds I spent becoming someone new at the <a href="http://www.nyrr.org/races-and-events/2016/new-balance-5th-avenue-mile">NYRR New Balance 5th Ave Mile</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The Chicago Marathon is about a month away. Kevin&rsquo;s training has been focused on both speed and middle distances. With that said, running about 55 to 60 miles a week has gotten me stronger, leaner, and healthier but it has not necessarily led me down the speedster path. While the week leading up to the mile race was focused on tuning the speed endurance for the mile, I wasn&rsquo;t in high hopes to run a fast mile. I was hoping to make a new personal best (5:06 previously), of course, but I wasn&rsquo;t sure if I could break the five minute barrier. I was still running high mileage and not tapering for this race, but I understood that the marathon is my main goal.</p>

<p>I was calm before the race but once the race started I got nervous. The younger age group heats went before me and as I was cheering for them I constantly kept looking at my watch to keep track of time. After my warmup I lined up with Nate, who was a few feet away, Kevin, who decided to live-feed his mile run, and Jose, who told me before the race he was going for 4:40 with 70 second splits per quarter mile.</p>

<p>Fantastic. Everyone has a plan and I&rsquo;ll stick with mine but I&rsquo;ll try to keep Jose and Nate in my sights. About ten seconds to go and everyone has their right hand on their left wrist ready to start their watch. We&rsquo;re off and it&rsquo;s exhilarating.</p>

<p>First quarter mile featured a slight downhill. It was about 70 or 71 seconds of a steady sprint and I kept thinking how easy it felt. I was so surprised because it&rsquo;s usually hard for me to hit that time and pace in training. Second quarter comes and I believe I saw 2:28/2:27 on the clock. I was on pace for a sub 5 minute mile and the thought of that happening midrace pumped me up. At this point there were already many runners breathing hard and slowing down. This makes sense because the second quarter was on an uphill. After recovering on the uphill came a downhill for the third quarter. I vaguely remember this part except that I pushed harder because of the downhill. It turned out, after looking at my race on Garmin, that this quarter was actually my slowest!</p>

<p>The last quarter was amazing. I quickly glanced at the clock on the road and read around 3:43, meaning that I had the sub 5 minute goal within reach.</p>

<p><img src="http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/5avemile.jpg" title="Cheer station at the .75 of a mile mark." alt="Cheer station at the .75 of a mile mark.">
Photo courtesy of NYRR.</p>

<p>The &frac34; of a mile mark was also the location where my team held the cheer station and they were loud. Screams and cheers motivated me to push and go faster. About 200 meters to go and I put in my final kick until the end. I cross the finished line, didn&rsquo;t stop my watch, and tried to absorb what had just happened. I didn&rsquo;t know the official time yet but I knew it was 4:55 or 4:56.</p>

<p><img src="http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/5avemile-solo.jpg" title="Finishing the race." alt="Finishing the race.">
Photo courtesy of NYRR and Gameface.</p>

<p>Perhaps the introduction was a bit dramatic; I didn&rsquo;t become someone new at the race. But I did not spend the past few months training hard to settle for anything less than the best I could do. The training since then have significantly changed. While training I now think, &ldquo;I ran 4:56 for the mile, I can push harder.&rdquo; And so far that&rsquo;s exactly what I&rsquo;ve done. I&rsquo;m still the same person but with a different mentality about myself; and so a different person.</p>

<p>Spending this race with my family and team meant a lot. We cheered each other on and we stayed for the whole event to watch the professionals. My father ran a fast mile in 5:34 and is doing so well in his age group. Bryan impressed himself with a 6:01 mile. He was really ecstatic about his time, but like I told him, I knew he was capable of running that fast. This race proved what believing in yourself can lead to.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BJ5vtsrDXhQ/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">6:01, 4:56, and 5:34 unofficial times for us at the New Balance 5th Ave Mile. Still the fastest but my brother and father are catching up too quickly! #queensdistance #nb5thavemile #mile #qdr #fam #sub5minutes #finally</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-09-03T17:32:26+00:00">Sep 3, 2016 at 10:32am PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br />
Regarding training the week leading up to race: there were two workouts that helped fine-tune the legs for the mile race.</p>

<p>Tuesday: 2 x 200m, 3 x 800m, mile
Both 200 meters came in at 36 seconds feeling nice and steady. The three 800 meters (half a mile) came in at 2:35.8, 2:35.9, and 2:31.9 and they were tough but not completely drained of energy. Then the mile was difficult. The goal was to hit a little bit under 5:30 but knowing full well that I was tired from the workout; ended up hitting 5:47.</p>

<p>Thursday: 2 x 400m, 4 x mile
This was intimidating because I wasn&rsquo;t if I would be 100% recovered with this kind of workout two days before the race. The 400 meters came in at 1:18.8 and 1:17.9; a steady 1:20 pace throughout but a kick for the last 100 meters. The miles were meant to tune my high speed and were broken up into 400 meter splits. The first 400 meters at marathon pace (about 1:35), the second at half marathon pace (about 1:30), the third at 5K pace (about 1:20), and the last 400 meters at mile pace (1:15). It&rsquo;ll be too long to write all the splits, but overall this went very well. It was tiring, for sure, but I managed to kick and end four miles at 1:17, 1:18. 1:18, 1:20. It was not at the 1:15 goal but the effort was there and that was enough to secure a strong mindset for the race.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s interesting to note that I never hit sub 2:30 for 800 meters in training and Kevin was surprised by how well I did. I guess by his estimations of the training, he expected around 4:59 to 5:01. Always setting the bar high.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scotland Run 10K and Youth Race]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/04/04/scotland-10k-and-youth-race/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-04T20:00:10-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/04/04/scotland-10k-and-youth-race</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another race, another personal best record broken. To be fair, I don&rsquo;t race too many 10Ks and the last one before the Scotland Run was in July of 2015. With all the training I&rsquo;ve done and my performances at the Washington Heights 5K and NYC Half, I expected good results. Of course, anything can happen during a race and this was race was no exception.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.nyrr.org/races-and-events/2016/scotland-run-10k">NYRR Scotland Run 10K</a> was the second club points race of the year and both our men&rsquo;s and women&rsquo;s competitive teams were already off to a great start. After the first club points race the men&rsquo;s team placed 8th in the A division, the women&rsquo;s team placed 4th in the B division, and both teams were hungry for more.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I get excited for every race, but club points races make even more adrenaline run through you than usual races. The most important part of these races is the team. It&rsquo;s great to know that when you&rsquo;re racing, you&rsquo;re not just racing for yourself but for your team. That&rsquo;s not to say that there&rsquo;s added pressure to perform well&ndash;we always help and support each other to run our best. That&rsquo;s what helps strengthen our bonds and boost our team to another level.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="6" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:42.4028268551% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BDtBDvLPPLC/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">35 Queens Distance Runners took on the Scotland 10K at Central Park and weathered the dreary weather to some great times!  QDR Men- 9th Place, A Division!  QDR Women- 1st Place, B Division!  Congratulations to everyone that came out to run today! #scotland10k #nyrr #thecrew #queensdistance #qdr #goforgold!</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Queens Distance Runners (@queensdistance) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-04-02T15:45:30+00:00">Apr 2, 2016 at 8:45am PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<h3>Scotland Run</h3>

<p>I met a few new runners in our team, said hi to Kevin and Jose who were working during the race, freaked out when I couldn&rsquo;t find the sticker to put on my bag, chilled when Maria tells me that it&rsquo;s a tag and not a sticker to add to the bag, and then started my warm up. For this race, I experimented with a slightly longer warm up that included very quick strides and some slower strides for a longer duration.</p>

<p>Kevin gave me a race strategy, but after a 5:51 first mile which felt surprisingly easy, I decided to maintain that pace instead of going a few seconds slower. My 5K split goal was 18:30 but I managed an 18:16 split. Everything was going well and I expected a slow 4th mile, but I was not expecting to slightly cramp up and not be able to breathe. After a few deep breaths I was back at it, running alongside another runner who kept me right on pace. Actually, I did not know how fast I was going for the last 2.2 miles but I knew I had to keep on attacking. Right around 5.70 miles into the race I began my kick, knowing there would only be about half a mile left. About 200m to go and I see Chaz running in the opposite direction cheering me on and I start my final kick. Final time of 36:34 and tied for third with Nate for Queens Distance.</p>

<h3>Youth Race</h3>

<p>Quickly after picking up my baggage, I run down to 59th and 5th Ave. to pick up my brother for his youth race. I was a bit worried about him coming to Central Park all by himself but it turned out that my sister accompanied him. It was very sweet of her, especially because she worked a night shift at her job. It&rsquo;s around 9:30am, we get some coffee and head to the start. After a quick pep talk, he was off running a 12:50 1.7 mile race. It&rsquo;s his first of a couple of races this year and I&rsquo;m really excited to see how he does at the Queens 10K!</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="6" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BDtEynUHUvT/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Great time this morning at the Scotland Run 10K! I had a course PR by over two minutes, and then Bryan ran 1.7 miles at the NYRR Youth Series race. Can&#39;t wait for when my brother starts catching up to me! #queensdistance #qdr #NYRR #scotlandRun #NYRRYRS #10k #runningbrothers</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-04-02T16:18:07+00:00">Apr 2, 2016 at 9:18am PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<p> <script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script></p>

<p>Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NYC Half and Another Milestone]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/03/20/united-airlines-nyc-half/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-20T19:43:32-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/03/20/united-airlines-nyc-half</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s 4:55 AM on a cold Sunday morning as I excitedly get ready for the NYRR United Airlines NYC Half. The prospect of having a great race made me nervous the whole morning and I couldn&rsquo;t keep my thoughts at bay. My father, who was about to tackle his first half marathon, and I get ready and leave, slowly running to the train station. As we exit the 59th St. station in Manhattan, the cold air sets a somber tone for the next few minutes until we meet other teammates. As we huddle together to stay warm we talk about our goals, how nervous we are, and how cold it is. It could&rsquo;ve been the pre-race jitters but I was shivering quite a lot, so much that I was afraid I might have been underprepared for this race.</p>

<p>As it turned out, after warming up for a bit and focusing on the race to come, everything calmed down. I sort of knew what I wanted to hit but I wasn&rsquo;t sure if I could it hit. This is not to say that I wasn&rsquo;t confident, but I did not feel like I was in the same shape I was back in October when I hit 1:20:25 for the Grete&rsquo;s Great Gallop half marathon. My goals consisted of first sub 1:21:00 and second sub 1:20:30, but Kevin (friend and coach) knew I could potentially hit sub 1:20:00 from the results of the workouts leading up to this race. It&rsquo;s also worth noting that I&rsquo;m focusing on 5K training and that I didn&rsquo;t really consider this race as a goal race. Weeks ago I wanted to use this race to evaluate where I am in my training and fitness, but it turned out so much better than that.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>My training fell into place after the Washington Heights 5K (18:05), hill training in San Francisco, and speed and tempo training a few days before the NYC Half. What helped the most was having my teammates and father around pre-race; everyone was so excited and motivated that it pushed me.</p>

<p>The race itself was amazing. This is my third time running this race, jumping down from 1:30:42 in 2014, to 1:24:50 in 2015, to 1:19:58 in 2016. As the race starts off I&rsquo;m immersed in the surrounding, the pack of runners closing around me, the early heavy breathings, and the sound of sneakers hitting the pavement. I hit a 5:49 second mile and I back off, knowing I have to stick to the game plan and knowing that there are more treacherous hills waiting for me. As I leave Central Park at mile 6, I start to feel it - a sluggish feeling overcoming me and slightly slowing me down. It was at this point that I actually wanted to speed up. So I opened a gel at this point and started a slow intake.</p>

<p>This next part of the race is always amazing. Running down to Times Square and then turning to the West Side Highway is filled with cheers, cameras, and so much excitement that you can&rsquo;t help but go faster. But&hellip; it was at this point that the wind started to pick up, and even though you are expecting it, it still hits you hard. Then I did something stupid around mile 9 and took in another bite of energy gel and water at the same time, causing me to choke for about 5 seconds until I recovered and was able to catch my breath. It&rsquo;s an odd feeling when you&rsquo;re running and think you should probably stop because it could be a serious issue, but your legs just keep on moving, sometimes even faster as if that would make the pain go away faster. (This same situation happened at the 60K when, before starting the last loop around Central Park, I took in too much water and choked. That time I did stop to recover - ultras aren&rsquo;t easy!)</p>

<p><img src="http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/nychalf-wsh.jpg" title="Running on the West Side Highway." alt="Running on the West Side Highway. Photo by Jared Mestre">
Photo by Jared Mestre</p>

<p>Three miles to go. Wait, am I at 9 miles or at 10 miles? Is that clock right? If I keep this up I can reach the 10 mile time range I need to hit sub 1:20. Let me do the math&hellip;.</p>

<p>Focus. I pushed all those thoughts aside and just kept going. It was around this point that my mind started to wander off and I just thought about catching up to the runner in front of me and passing him, and then the next runner, and so on. It wasn&rsquo;t until mile 11.5 or so that I saw the 1:20:00 pacer and group! So I slowly speed up trying to catch this group and I managed to reach them right before the 12th mile. I thought about sticking with them the whole way and hitting sub 1:20 in that manner, but what if the pacer was off? And, more importantly, am I really pushing myself as much as I possibly can? Definitely not. I decided to just fly away, picking up speed as I pass the last water station and a volunteer yells, &ldquo;GO QUEENS DISTANCE!&rdquo;, and picking up even more speed as I head into the tunnel and last mile. I felt like I was cruising in the tunnel, easily maintaining a high speed which only encouraged me to go faster&hellip; and then we exit the tunnel. That last uphill at the exit may be small but it can quickly drain you. Not only does it slow you down, but it makes it that much harder to pick up speed again.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/nychalf-200m.jpg" width="300" height="450" title="200 meters to go!" alt="200 meters to go!"></p>

<p>600 meters to go and I pick it up again. 400 meters to go and it&rsquo;s only one lap of a track, right? 200 meters to go and I see and hear my family cheering for me. This last part was the most painful and disappointing part simply because I could not kick as hard as I wanted to, but I probably went just as fast and didn&rsquo;t notice. The time on the clock read 1:20:&ndash; with about 15 seconds or so. As it was pointed out, the sigh of relief after finishing was real.</p>

<p>Unofficial time? 1:20:02. Much faster than expected and better than if I stayed with the pacer. It actually wasn&rsquo;t until later when fellow teammate Marie messaged me that the times were updated, and those 3 annoying seconds which would&rsquo;ve haunted me and kept me up at night, turned into 2 seconds under 1:20. It&rsquo;s amazing and I&rsquo;ve just hit a huge milestone in my training, but I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;ve quite let that sink in yet. It&rsquo;s not exactly disbelief, but I just can&rsquo;t describe this feeling.</p>

<p>My father had an amazing half marathon debut in 1:33:30 and I&rsquo;m ecstatic for him. Perhaps he&rsquo;ll run the Queens Marathon or maybe even the NYC Marathon&mdash;I can&rsquo;t wait to see what he does next!</p>

<p><img src="http://edwinguzman.github.io/images/blog-images/nychalf-dad.jpg" title="Post-race with my father." alt="Post-race with my father."></p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t think of a better way to start this running blog post series.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Hope]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/03/16/a-new-hope/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-16T21:59:26-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/03/16/a-new-hope</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My last personal blog post was written on March 7th, 2015. Over a year ago. I made an attempt to write more but that didn&rsquo;t happen, at least not for my personal blog.</p>

<p>That blog post mentioned how I had written one blog post, how I was in the middle of writing two more,  and how I was not too happy then.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s been a year and so much has changed. I have written <a href="http://www.nypl.org/blog/author/1269">seven blog posts</a> for nypl.org, two on running and five on coding; I have grown as a runner in 2015 and in the past three months of 2016; I ran the LA Marathon in February; I went to San Francisco last week to attend O'Reilly Fluent Conference; I just went on a date with my mom to see On Your Feet!; I have met so many other runners who motivate me; I&rsquo;ve helped my dad get on a running agenda and will race his first half marathon at the NYRR NYC Half and possibly run the Queens Marathon; and I am happy.</p>

<p>More biking, running, and coding.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
