<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Nyc | Coding and Running]]></title>
  <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/categories/nyc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-03-18T21:29:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Edwin Guzman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2017 Fall Marathons Recap]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2017/11/20/fall-marathons-recap/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-20T22:28:08-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2017/11/20/fall-marathons-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Chicago</h2>

<p>I was 17 miles into the Chicago Marathon when I panicked. I was cruising miles 11 through 15 at low 6:20s pace per mile, just barely reaching into the marathon goal pace of 6:17 pace per mile. Suddenly, I felt an intense pain in my left abdomen. I&rsquo;ve felt this pain before when I tried to race, mostly untrained and recovering from an injury, at the 2016 Brooklyn Half. I was forced to stop and walk the pain away. Naturally, I didn&rsquo;t want that to happen again during this marathon, so I panicked.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='/images/blog-images/chicago-expo.jpg' width='450' height='550' title='At the Chicago Marathon expo.'><span class='caption-text'>At the Chicago Marathon expo.</span></span></p>

<p>I tried to battle one bad thought after another; but once the pain felt unbearable, I just had to stop and walk it off. The pain went away soon after. I gradually returned to a nice rhythm, hitting a 6:44 19th mile. Unfortunately, I didn&rsquo;t mentally recover from that setback and, along with my body giving up and not willing to keep running fast, I gave up. The first, second, and third goal for the race slipped away and so did my resolve to finish—I just wanted to walk away and try again at a later date. But I couldn’t quit with all the training and everything else I went through in the past few months.</p>

<p>Days like these when everything goes awry at a goal race happen. Still, you should make the best out of the situation. It was hard to. I&rsquo;m not sure what I would&rsquo;ve done if it wasn&rsquo;t for those helping me right after the marathon. Words of encouragement go a long way, but I couldn&rsquo;t help being upset. Being upset is acceptable. But, not seeing my teammates after they finished their own races was unacceptable. I took the next hour or so to try to rationalize the unexpected disappointment before making my way to the post-marathon meet-up spot.</p>

<p>The following day I tried to figure out what went wrong. I wasn&rsquo;t upset about not meeting my goals; I was (irrationally) upset about letting others down. I was upset about all the time and effort I put in every day with nothing to show. I was upset about giving up.</p>

<p>Looking back now, all those positive and negative feelings were useful. They gave me a deeper appreciation for what I&rsquo;m trying to accomplish. Until the day comes when I️ do meet my goals, it&rsquo;s just a matter of working hard and looking toward the future.</p>

<h2>Training</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/blog-images/20-miler-lr.png' width='425' height='525' title='Long Run - 20 miler in Central Park'><span class='caption-text'>Long Run - 20 miler in Central Park</span></span></p>

<p>This past marathon training cycle was the hardest one yet. Instead of doing a seven day training cycle with one or two rest days, I had an 11- or 12-day training cycle with one rest day in between. I practically ran everyday for over a week, and that was new to me. I also incorporated a lot of upper and lower body strength training. The most enjoyable form of cross training was climbing high walls and solving problems bouldering. Some of my favorite running workouts were the 20 milers where I averaged around 6:35 pace per mile, something I didn’t get close to doing last year. I even set a personal best at the NYRR 18 mile tune-up averaging a 6:23 pace, which helped boost my confidence for the Chicago Marathon.</p>

<p>When I look back at the past few months, I realized that getting through all that work was not difficult. Waking up before 5 AM to start my long runs wasn’t hard. Working out twice a day wasn’t hard. Eating better to maintain shape, recover, and fuel for the next run wasn’t hard. What was hard, however, was going through agony and emotional distress that came from the <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/09/04/politics/daca-dreamers-immigration-program/index.html">dismantling of DACA</a>.</p>

<p>DACA was rescinded and I was devastated. Approximately 800,000 people in the U.S. with DACA are now in a state of limbo regarding their residency in a country they call home. Those with DACA just have to keep living day to day like everyone else, knowing that at a moment&rsquo;s notice they can be deported to their &lsquo;home&rsquo; country. At work we launched a <a href="https://www.nypl.org/discovery">project</a> I had been working on for over a year, but I couldn’t be happy about the launch because it happened the same day. It was a dark time, and I wanted to be alone to make sense of the situation.</p>

<p>That’s not to say I didn’t have support. Coworkers, friends, and family members reached out and helped spread positive messages—a coworker&rsquo;s simple tweet was so moving that it left me speechless and teary in the office. Everything was greatly appreciated.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='/images/blog-images/dismantlingdaca.png' width='350' height='400' title='<a href="http://latinousa.org/episode/dismantling-daca/">Dismantling DACA Podcast</a><br>Image Courtesy of NPR Latino USA'><span class='caption-text'><a href="http://latinousa.org/episode/dismantling-daca/">Dismantling DACA Podcast</a><br>Image Courtesy of NPR Latino USA</span></span></p>

<p>What worried me the most was what the younger generation is going through. Most are still in school and don’t have a plan after graduation. That realization didn’t hit me until an <a href="http://latinousa.org/episode/dismantling-daca/">NPR podcast</a> made me tear up during a run. Listening about what others are going through and remembering what it was like hurt. I am glad, however, that we have communities to help those who need it.</p>

<p>I’m at a point where I’m doing what I love, and that’s not something I can take for granted. I never felt more like myself waking up before 5 AM and arriving at Flushing Meadow Park by 5:30 to start a 20 miler, or going through a tough speed session in the morning and then a strength session in the afternoon. Mentally going through training like a &ldquo;professional&rdquo;, looking forward to every run, and maintaining a consistent schedule made me feel unstoppable. I made everything a habit and cared enough that those day to day habits were not difficult to accomplish. Even though this was the first time I trained like this, it felt natural.</p>

<h2>NYC</h2>

<p>I have so much to say about the NYC Marathon that I cannot write it all down. I️ had to first recover from the Chicago Marathon. Two weeks after the race, I️ tested out the legs by doing two medium long runs. I️ felt confident enough to be able to give another decent shot at the marathon. At a certain point during the NYC marathon, however, I started to feel my legs seizing up, so I took it easy aiming just to finish and have fun.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BbBBz7chuWI/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Here we go again! The Guzman trio are ready for this weekend’s races. Bryan is racing the Dash to the Finish 5K, and my dad and I are racing the NYC Marathon. • It’s time to get over the disappointment at Chicago and give the marathon another shot. It’s hard not to be positive with my teammates’ and coworkers’ support. #queensdistance #nycmarathon #abbotdash5k #teamwork</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A post shared by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2017-11-03T02:18:57+00:00">Nov 2, 2017 at 7:18pm PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<p> <script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script></p>

<p>It’s difficult to not enjoy and have fun racing a marathon where you live. My coworker Greg made a poster of the marathon course highlighting what time I’d be at specific locations. I was able to catch him in the Bronx cheering, as well as other coworkers in Brooklyn and Manhattan. My cousins, aunts, uncles, and grandmother who live in the Bronx were set up in the same location where they, to my surprise, were located last year. Teammates volunteered at Mile 14 and 15 in Queens and passing them gave me motivation before tackling the Queensboro Bridge. And my family was also located right before the Queensboro Bridge and at later at Mile 25.5. It’s the fourth year consecutive year they come out for me. All the love, best wishes, and support is what makes the NYC Marathon my favorite marathon.</p>

<h2>Team</h2>

<p>I may not have accomplished the specific time that I wanted to run at the Chicago Marathon, but I accomplished so much more. It’s the drive and encouragement that I️, along with Kevin and Maria, try to give everyone in our team that makes them strive for more. So when I hear about PRs, surpassed expectations, or just completing a marathon which they’ve always dreamed of doing, I know I’m heading in the right direction helping them out.</p>

<p>This is the first (and maybe last) blog post of this year, but suffice it to say that this whole year culminated at a high point at the NYC Marathon. My outlook on DACA being rescinded and the disappointment at the Chicago Marathon is the same as all aspects in my life right now — optimistic and striving for more.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BbQYo1chqV4/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">We started 2017 by running and finishing the Boston Marathon side-by-side, and now we finished the year by both running the NYC Marathon. Never take anything for granted. • #bostonmarathon #tcsnycmarathon #likefatherlikeson</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A post shared by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2017-11-09T01:27:02+00:00">Nov 8, 2017 at 5:27pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>


<p> <script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script></p>

<p>* A big thanks to everyone who supported me in the past few months and to those who helped look over this post!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2016 NYC Marathon: Still Trying to Find Myself]]></title>
    <link href="http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/11/17/2016-nyc-marathon-still-trying-to-find-myself/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-17T23:20:44-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://edwinguzman.github.io/blog/2016/11/17/2016-nyc-marathon-still-trying-to-find-myself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been close to two weeks after the NYC marathon and I still don&rsquo;t know how to put everything that has happened into words. The feelings of pride, happiness, sadness, determination, and emptiness still lingers. The love outweighs the negativity but I can&rsquo;t help and feel slightly upset about how this training cycle concluded. Lots of factors went into the back-to-back Chicago and NYC marathon races and I can only learn from the experience.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Bad</h2>

<p>Quick statistics: In 2015 I ran the NYC Marathon in 2:59:24 and then two weeks later the NYRR 60K in 4:37:41. This year, I ran the Chicago Marathon in 2:58:05 (a PR) and then the NYC Marathon in 3:00:55.</p>

<p>I’m not sure how I did what I did last year, considering I feel fitter and stronger this year. A week before the NYC Marathon, however, I felt an intense pain in my right inner thigh, very close to the groin. I then took a few days off to rest well which halted my training, but I was suppose to rest and taper anyways. I was four miles into the NYC Marathon when I felt a slight pull and feelings of pain again. It was then that I knew that I had to slow down because it would be a tough marathon.</p>

<p>But, injury aside, I didn’t feel prepared for NYC. I don’t believe I lost any fitness from the Chicago Marathon which was about 4 weeks prior to NYC. Now that I had time to think about it, I was disappointed about how the Chicago Marathon unfolded and I was afraid of repeating the same situation in NYC. Luckily, because I went through it just recently, I felt better about failing this time around.</p>

<h2>The Good</h2>

<p>I had two Boston Qualifying races about one month apart, I ran with a bigger Queens Distance team, I saw many friends and family along the course, and I was able to share this marathon experience with my father who ran his first NYC Marathon. All of that made this NYC Marathon my favorite marathon yet. It was an incredible feeling to go through all of that in a span of a few hours, a fraction of which was the actual race.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:62.4537037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BMX9wmSjZxG/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Father and son ✌🏼️ Both Local Competitive 💪🏼 We trained hard, earned our spots, and now it&#39;s time: TCS NYC Marathon!🏃🏻🏃🏻 Not many can say that they will run a marathon with their father and for that I&#39;m truly grateful. #likefatherlikeson #queensdistance #tcsnycmarathon #marathoners #fam #😭</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-11-04T04:15:10+00:00">Nov 3, 2016 at 9:15pm PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<h1>TCS NYC Marathon</h1>

<p>My team set up another bus shuttle ride to Staten Island this year and it was a sleepy joy to meetup with teammates and other runners all going to run NYC, either again or for the first time. Being surrounded by first timers made the trip uneasy because I caught their nervousness but later regained control. After unloading, some of us headed to the Local Competitor area which now had so many Queens Distance runners. My father was with me this entire time and he was in awe about everything, especially since I kept telling him about everything that was around us. That truly made the experience amazing; how many can say they started off the NYC Marathon with their father?</p>

<p>The race started off well though it might’ve been faster that what I wanted to start off at. As I mentioned above, the slight pain at mile 4 made me settle into a steadier pace. Everything was going well and I was really enjoying the crowd. I pinned a small Mexican flag on my chest and I kept hearing “vamos Mexico!” which really filled me up with pride. (Note: I should really try adding my name next time.)</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BMff3NSD-SE/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Probably the most painful marathon I&#39;ve ever ran but still trying to smile. 🇲🇽 #queensdistance #tcsnycmarathon #stilllookinggood #vamosmexico</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-11-07T02:27:51+00:00">Nov 6, 2016 at 6:27pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<p>After the halfway point we were in Queens where I saw so many friends cheering either at the Mile 14 water station, in the streets, or at the mile 15 Queens Center for Progress cheering station. And then, it got lonely and painful. I started the slow and long trek up the Queensboro bridge and about a fourth of the way up, I was starting to get really tired, and this was with me slowing down. My heart rate just spiked up and I was working way too hard. It was around this point that Marie tapped me on my elbow as she sped on in front of me. It was great seeing her there and hoping she’d have a good marathon.</p>

<p>I soon after regain composure when I made it to 1st Ave. where one of my coworkers was waiting for me but I didn’t hear him! Going up 1st Ave. was tough, especially when I felt I was going at a steady 6:30 pace but was actually closer to 6:50 pace. That 20 second pace difference is very noticeable at this point as you’re tired but want to keep pushing. Fine, not a big deal, just need to keep running and make it at least past the Bronx; if I get back to Manhattan on 5th Ave. in one piece I’ll be happy.</p>

<p>I have a clear image of the first moment I stepped into the Bronx. During our training runs we run on the pedestrian side of the bridge and so we never get to run on the actual course. So as I stepped into the Bronx I now have this image of the first left corner and seeing a huge crowd waiting for us. The Bronx is mentally easily as I know all the turns very, very well… and so I just tune off and run. But, as I was approaching the Western Beef and the final turns in the Bronx, I kept hearing my name. I knew that Elizabeth and Anthony (fellow teammates) were going to wait for us in the Bronx at mile 21 but it was not mile 21 yet. So I look around and I clearly see my grandma and my cousin Nayeli. I’m a bit confused and I turn around again and I see my other cousins, aunts, and uncles and I’m so surprised. This is the part that I can’t describe; I was surprised, in euphoria, and too emotional. I began to choke a bit as I felt a sob coming on but just had to put that aside and try to finish well&ndash;I didn’t want them cheering for me on a run which could have ended worse than it did.</p>

<p>With that, I did make it to Manhattan in one piece. It was running down 5th Ave. that further broke me down as I took a few walking breaks due to a mixture of fatigue and pain in my leg (not necessarily cramping since that came later around mile 24). Eventually, I made my way to the end right after waving at my family who were cheering for me on 59th St.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:37.4537037037% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BMe-3HajHlP/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">And we&#39;re done! It was a very tough marathon, especially coming off Chicago in early October, but my heart was all in it. So even though I didn&#39;t reach my goal, I still Boston Qualified and had the most fun I ever had in a marathon. I tried to focus more on everyone who was out there cheering and calling my name. It was even better knowing how many friends were tracking me #nopressure. And when I got to mile 20 in the Bronx I saw my family there! My abuelita, my aunts and uncles, and cousins. It was so unexpected that I choked up and got teary 😭. And seeing my mom, aunt, and siblings near the end again was awesome. So a huge thank you to everyone! ❤️ And a great sign by my sister @karennhaze. #likefatherlikeson #queensdistance #tcsnycmarathon #fam #love #marathoners #seeyousoonboston</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by Edwin (@algorhythm19) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-11-06T21:39:29+00:00">Nov 6, 2016 at 1:39pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p><br /></p>

<h2>Closing the Year</h2>

<p>Pain. I finished the marathon cycle in a lot of pain. I have never felt that much pain in my legs after completing a marathon and I hope not to feel that again. I was trying to wait for my father but only managed to bump into Jose, Catherine, and Lori. The walk to get the poncho and exit Central Park was awful. I couldn’t move too fast and if I did it just made the pain worse.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/blog-images/2016-nyc-marathon.jpg" width="450" height="600" title="&lsquo;Reunited with my father after the NYC Marathon.&rsquo; &lsquo;Reunited with my father after the NYC Marathon.&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve gotten up to this point and are wondering about the title, so am I. I had two great marathons which other runners would love to achieve, but I am personally not satisfied with the execution. As I mentioned before, they were great times but I faded after about 20 miles into both races. What I&rsquo;m truly getting at is that I&rsquo;m still trying to find myself as a runner. It sounds banal but I&rsquo;m just learning how competitive and how much more I want to achieve that I don&rsquo;t know where I&rsquo;ll stop, if at all.</p>

<p>Everyone learns something about themselves after running a marathon; you never really are the same after crossing the finish line. It wasn&rsquo;t so much this race but the whole experience that really changed me.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
